# Ben Baker

## Software Engineer

 $978-204-4749 \cdot bbakercello@gmail.com \cdot Lowell, MA \cdot \underline{https://github.com/bbakercello} \cdot \underline{https://www.linkedin.com/in/ben-baker-cello/linkedin.com/in/ben-ba$ 

I'm a software engineer who loves developing core infrastructures of technological products. I specialize in Javascript technologies (MERN stack - MongoDB, Express JS, React JS, Node JS) to build complete web applications. I develop elegant solutions using open source tools and proactively look for ways to make systems run efficiently through continuous delivery and automated testing. In my free time as a cellist and composer, I write electronic pieces of music using modular synthesizers and digital instruments.

#### **SKILLS**

Languages - JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Python, SQL, Mongo, JSON, Typescript, EJS, DTL | Database - PostgreSQL, MongoDB Libraries and Frameworks - React, Redux, NextJS, Express.js, Django, Jquery, Bootstrap, Semantic UI, Bulma, TailwindCSS Other - RESTful Routing, JSON api

### SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS

**Anonimusic** | Anonymous audio forum

September 2022

- Created a session-based music sharing platform using Express and MongoDB on the backend and Cloudinary and React on the front-end
- Researched and implemented open-source components such as useState, Collapsible and React Audio Player to provide the user with an accessible and simple interface
- Wrote functions to dynamically generate randomized user names upon session start as well as conditional features such as username colors, permissions and time-stamped comments
- Pair programmed front end in duos and trios to learn and teach new component libraries and continuosly monitor git flow of branches between developers
- Styled and created the visual aspects using CSS and React Bootstrap

**Body Bell Records** | Indie-Electronic Record Label application

October 2022

- Created a full-stack record label site using NextJS, Express, MongoDB, Spotify API, TailwindCSS and HeadlessUI to present an
  artistic and clean UI
- Self taught new technologies such as NextJS and TailwindCSS in order to expand knowledge and render server side data making user experience faster
- Implemented Spotify user authentication and used API syntax to query artist data

**LandPost** | Nature-focused social media platform

August 2022

- Led back-end programming in collaborative project to create entity relationships and program dynamic content display based off of user credentials and current session status
- Made RESTful API fetch calls to an Express, MongoDB, Node.js backend handling all create, read, update, delete (CRUD) operations, and tested all backend routes during development using Postman
- Pair programmed front and back ends in duos to create general architecture of application and monitor state of git repositories
- Used Mongoose to define schemas for MongoDB collections

### **Ratscrew** | Fully interactive card game

August 2022

- Created a front-end browser-based page with Javascript, HTML and CSS to program a fun twist on the classic card game of War with additional rules for face cards
- Implemented JavaScript for game-mechanic functions and DOM manipulation to render card elements, asses win/loss conditions and provide user with game state information
- Formalized thorough comments throughout JavaScript to ensure ease of future code refactoring and potential collaborations on project

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Johnson String Instrument Quality Control and Fulfillment Director | Waltham, MA

June 2019 - July 2022

Assumed full managerial responsibility of the entire workshop as a result of manpower overturn. Effectively developed a new
online inventory system using Trello which led to more efficient outgoing order processes as well as overall positive upturn in
customer satisfaction and feedback.

- Consulted shipping, sales and school service departments to develop more economical product storage policies. Directed
  workshop staff in implementation of new systems resulting in a more effective workflow as well as room for internal company
  growth.
- Inspected and prepared all outgoing instruments to insure company standards are exceeded. Delegated fulfillment tasks to staff leading to gaining a larger customer base with a same-day-shipping option.

## **AP Intego** Customer Service Representative | Rochester, New York | Boston, MA

June 2015 - July 2017

- Took lead in management of payroll errors in Intuit billing system leading to a more functional customer service department. Error management led directly to improved retention and an overall increase in new clients.
- Collaborated with team members to solve data flow issues between insurance carrier sites and hosted systems. Solutions for data management resulted in stronger business relationships with insurance carriers.
- Communicated with customers via email to provide assistance in uploading payroll data and identifying insurance policy statuses for small businesses resulting in higher company reviews and stronger relations.

## **Boston Music Project** Customer Service Representative | Boston, MA

**September 2017 - May 2019** 

- Developed exercises and repertoire for classroom ensembles on a daily basis. Engaging instruction led to more advanced aural skills and understandings of beginning music theory.
- Led chamber music sessions to small groups of beginning and intermediate students. Instruction led to increased communication skills and a greater appreciation for the arts.
- Adjusted technique quickly and gently when teaching large groups while catering to each individual's learning styles. One on one attention resulted in greater physical awareness and a more relaxed approach to the instrument.

#### **EDUCATION**

## GENERAL ASSEMBLY | REMOTE

Software Engineering Immersive

**July 2022 - October 2022** 

Full-stack software engineering immersive student in an intensive, twelve-week, 450+ hour program focused on product development fundamentals, object-oriented programming, MVC frameworks, data modeling, and team collaboration strategies. Developed a portfolio of individual and group projects.

Boston Conservatory at Berklee | Boston, MA

Master of Contemporary Classical Music (MM)

August 2017 - May 2019

The Eastman School of Music | Rochester, NY

Bachelor of Cello Performance (MM)

August 2012 - May 2016